[Music]
a wide leg pant with no side seam is an
easy garment to put together and sew the
elastic waist makes it super comfortable
and it looks good in many types of
fabric hi i'm angela wolf let me show
you how easy it is to make these super
flattering pants
i'm using the taper and wide leg pant
pattern from christine johnson patterns
but these techniques would work for any
similar pattern style
these pants are easy because there's
only one pattern piece to work with
take a look at the grain line on the
pattern piece i've lined this up with
the grain line on the fabric the grain
line is typically parallel to the
selvage this will mean the drape of your
pants will look its best here's the
pattern piece all cut out with the
notches and hem markings transferred
these will help us match the pieces up
later on you can see on the pattern that
this is the inseam and there's no
outside leg seam something to remember
if you're using a woven fabric that has
no stretch like i am choose a waist size
that's large enough to get over your
hips otherwise it's going to be a real
struggle to pull those pants on we're
going to start with the inseam with
right sides of the fabric together line
up the notches and pin the front leg to
the back leg
line up the seam allowance with the 5 8
inch marking back stitch and stitch all
the way from the crotch to the hem i'm
using a contrasting thread but you
choose a matching color
finish the seam allowances i'm going to
trim the seam allowances with pinking
shears you could use an overlock stitch
a zigzag stitch or a serger whatever you
prefer
look for the triple notches on the
crotch seam this is the back of the
pants press the seam allowance in this
direction
okay one leg down and one to go just
follow the same steps again for the
second pant leg once you've done that
you'll join the two legs together at the
crotch seam have one pant leg with the
wrong side facing out and one pant leg
with the right side facing out
insert the leg with the right side
facing out into this pant leg
line up both in seams
and pin
you can see both of these are wrong
sides out now
line up the notches remember one notch
refers to the front of the pant place a
pin
and these triple notches refer to the
back
pin all the way around this crotch seam
next you'll stitch along this entire
crotch curve starting at the top edge
back stitch once or twice and stitch all
the way around when you get to the
inseam make sure both the seam
allowances are folded toward the back of
the pants
[Music]
again you'll finish the seam edge just
like before and then press the crotch
seam to one side
a sleeve board or a full-size ironing
board is perfect for this job
next attach the elastic to the waistline
start by measuring the elastic around
your waistline to determine how tight
you want the elastic and pin
mark where the elastic meets
cross the elastic pieces lining up the
markings and zigzag stitch back and
forth
[Music]
trim off the excess elastic now with a
fabric pen make marks on the elastic
center back and center front
[Music]
line the elastic up along the wrong side
of the fabric
matching up the center front seam
with the center front marking on the
elastic
and the center back marking with the
center back of the pants stretch the
elastic and add a few pins
this will help to ease the elastic in
evenly all the way around the waistband
stitch the elastic to the fabric with a
zigzag stitch of 1.4 length and 3.5
width as you do this make sure to
stretch the elastic to match the length
of the fabric
finish your edge and then turn under the
elastic toward the wrong side of the
fabric
pin at the center back seam
and the center front
[Music]
and let's just add one pin to each side
line up the edge of the presser foot
with the edge of the elastic and stitch
the bottom edge of the elastic to the
fabric with a slightly bigger zigzag
stitch of 1.8 long and 4.5 wide make
sure the elastic butts up to the fold
and again
stretch the elastic to match the length
of the fabric stitch over the first
stitch just a little and back stitch
and the waist is finished
the final step is hemming your pants
using the hem allowance marking
press the fabric up toward the wrong
side of the fabric tuck under the raw
edge half an inch and press
at the machine check to make sure the
needle will just catch the folded hem
allowance edge on the right side of the
fabric top stitch the hem in place with
a straight stitch of 3.5 to keep that
line of stitching straight use the
guides on your sewing machine
give the hem one more pressing and the
pants are finished you have made a great
pair of pants in a couple of hours
thanks for watching get expert sewing
instruction free resources and supplies
for your next project by clicking the i
in the top right corner of this video
[Music]